From Daily Wire published April
12 2026 What America Learned
from Negotiations with Iran What
America Learned from
Negotiations with Iran The
Iranians need to recognize that
the realities on the ground in
Iran do not match their
assumptions heading into the
negotiations By Mary Margaret
Olihan April 12 2026 dailywire
com Listen to this article
Washington The marathon
negotiations between the United
States and Iran in Pakistan
didn't lead to a peace deal but
American leadership came away
with one major conclusion Iran
is delusional about its standing
in negotiations Vice President J
D Vance will soon arrive back in
Washington and President Donald
Trump has upped the ante
declaring a complete blockade of
the Strait of Hormuz The
negotiations helped the United
States understand just how
little Iran understood their
situation U S officials told the
Daily Wire Iran failed to
recognize the reality of the
situation on the ground the
officials say and has not come
to terms with the fact that its
inability to ever have a nuclear
weapon is a primary American
objective A U S official said
Vance entered the negotiations
well aware that the United
States and Iran had hardly
interacted with one another for
half a century Vance went into
the 21 hours of negotiations
with plans to test the
counterparties and assess what
they believed their situation
was Vance probed their
vulnerabilities and Trump is now
testing those vulnerabilities
the official said and the world
will see whether the Iranians
recognize reality The meeting
with Iran began early in the
morning and lasted throughout
the night close to 20 hours I
could go into great detail and
talk about much that has been
gotten but there is only one
thing that matters Iran is
unwilling to give up its nuclear
ambitions the president said In
many ways the points that were
agreed to are better than us
continuing our military
operations to conclusion but all
of those points don't matter
compared to allowing nuclear
power to be in the hands of such
volatile difficult unpredictable
people One of the vice
president's main goals heading
into the talks was for both the
United States and Iran to get to
a mutual understanding on each
country's objectives and their
negotiating space the first U S
official explained Though the
conversations were tough the
official said by the end the
negotiators had completed a
productive exchange of proposals
U S Vice President J D Vance
talks to Pakistan's Chief of
Defense Forces and Chief of Army
Staff Field Marshal Asim Munir
and Pakistan's Deputy Prime
Minister and Foreign Minister
Mohammad Ishaq Dar C before
boarding Air Force Two after
attending talks on Iran and
Islamabad on April 12 2026 photo
by Jacqueline Martin AFP via
Getty Images Vance also believed
that deal should be acceptable
to the Iranians and said
publicly that he hopes they will
accept it Another key point of
the weekend negotiations Vance
probed the Iranian assessment of
their own position and
discovered that they
fundamentally misunderstood
their own position walking into
the negotiations That was why
the vice president left
Islamabad after he gave that
final offer If the Iranians
believe they have leverage that
they do not have the official
said no deal is achievable And
before they are ready to
entertain a serious offer the
Iranians need to recognize that
the realities on the ground in
Iran do not match their
assumptions heading into the
negotiations The simple fact is
that we need to see an
affirmative commitment that they
will not seek a nuclear weapon
and they will not seek the tools
that would enable them to
quickly achieve a nuclear weapon
Vance told reporters as he
departed Pakistan That is the
core goal of the president of
the United States and that's
what we've tried to achieve
through these negotiations We
leave here and we leave here
with a very simple proposal a
method of understanding that is
our final and best offer We'll
see if the Iranians accept it
The White House national
security team has come up with a
plan in consultation with the
president intended to break the
Iranian closure of the Strait of
Hormuz and at the same time
challenge the idea that the
Strait of Hormuz can distract
from the main issue Iran's
nuclear program The vice
president is hopeful that Iran
recognizes that the deal they
have been presented is in both
parties interest the official
said A separate UA official
outlined the United States red
lines to the Daily Wire Iran
must end all uranium enrichment
dismantle all major nuclear
enrichment facilities retrieve
highly enriched uranium accept a
broader peace security and de
escalation framework that
includes regional allies end
funding for the terrorist
proxies Hamas Hezbollah and the
Houthis and fully open the
Strait of Hormuz charging no
tolls for passage There is a
deal still on the table the U S
official noted and the vice
president's statement emphasized
that It now remains up to the
Iranians whether or not they
accept it